George Alder Blumer correspondence
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
George Alder Blumer correspondence
1886-1951
1886-1896
Ms Coll 50
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
0.25
(1 box)
These letters to George Alder Blumer are mainly about the American Medico-Psychological Association and the American Journal of Insanity, edited by Blumer. Several of the writers were, like Blumer, administrators of psychiatric hospitals in the United States and abroad.
Blumer, G. Alder (George Alder), 1857-1940
Scope and Contents
These letters to George Alder Blumer are mainly about the American Medico-Psychological Association and the Journal of Insanity. Several of the writers were, like Blumer, administrators of psychiatric hospitals in the United States and abroad.
Biographical / Historical
George Alder Blumer (also known as G. Alder Blumer) was born in Sunderland, England in 1857. He attended the medical school of the University of Edinburgh for one year before he came to the United States, and completed his medical education at the University of Pennsylvania in 1879. After a year of residency at Lankenau Hospital, Philadelphia, he was offered a position at the New York State Lunatic Asylum in Utica, New York, later the Utica State Hospital. When the superintendent Dr. John P. Gray died in 1886, Blumer assumed the superintendency. Blumer intervened when the New York State Commission on Lunacy threatened to take over the American Journal of Insanity founded by Amariah Brigham in 1844 and owned by the hospital. Blumer arranged for the American Medico-Psychological Association, now the American Psychiatric Association, to purchase the journal, now the American Journal of Psychiatry. Blumer served a number of years as editor. In 1899, he became superintendent of the private Butler Hospital in Providence, R.I., a post he held until his retirement in 1921. He served as president of the American Psychiatric Association in 1903-1904. As an asylum director he became known for his humanitarian treatment of patients.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Most of the letters were given by Miss Mary Blumer, daughter of George Alder Blumer, to George Alder Blumer's cousin, George Blumer, former dean of Yale School of Medicine, who gave them to the Historical Library in April 1951. The Osler letters have a different provenance.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Medical publishing; Medicine -- Societies, etc.; Mental illness; Psychiatric hospitals; Psychiatry -- Periodicals; Correspondence; Physicians; Psychiatrists; Blandford, G. Fielding (George Fielding), 1829-1911; Blumer, G. Alder (George Alder), 1857-1940; Blumer, George, 1872-1962; Bramwell, Byrom, Sir, 1847-1931; Chapin, John B. (John Bassett), 1829-1918; Chauvin, P. S.; Clouston, T. S. (Thomas Smith), 1840-1915; Earle, Pliny, 1809-1892; Hurd, Henry M. (Henry Mills), 1843-1927; Needham, F. (Frederick), 1836-1924; Osler, William, Sir, 1849-1919; Parant, Victor, 1848-1924; Tuke, Daniel Hack, 1827-1895; Urquhart, Alexander Reid, 1852-1917; Yellowlees, D. (David); American Medico-Psychological Association; American Psychiatric Association; New York (State). State Lunatic Asylum
- Letters of transmission: Correspondence of George Blumer and Mary Blumer with John Fulton, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Six items.
- Blandford, G. Fielding, London, to George Alder Blumer, 1891 March 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Blumer, George, New Haven, to George Alder Blumer, Providence, 1913 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Partly regarding William Osler's visit to New Haven and the "Kernan matter."
- Bramwell, Byrom, Edinburgh, 5 letters to George Alder Blumer, 1886-1891 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Chapin, John B., Philadelphia, to George Alder Blumer, 1891 September 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Chauvin, P. S., Mauritius, to George Alder Blumer, 1892 November 10 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Clouston, Thomas Smith, Sir, Edinburgh, to G. Alder Blumer, 1891 March 4 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Earle, Pliny, Northampton, Mass., 5 letters to George Alder Blumer, 1891 February 3 - 1891 December 18 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Some of the content concerns a series of letters that Pliny Earle received from Amariah Brigham, who founded the Journal of Insanity.
- Hurd, Henry M., Baltimore, 3 letters to George Alder Blumer, 1896 August 17-1896 September 7 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Needham, Frederick, Sir, Gloucester, England to George Alder Blumer, 1891 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Osler, William, Sir, 14 letters to George Alder Blumer, 1896 June 10 - 1917 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  These letters were sent by George Alder Blumer to Harvey Cushing in 1920 and returned. They then were sent by Dr. Arthur H. Ruggles, Providence, to John F. Fulton, in September 1958. Folder includes George Alder Blumer to Harvey Cushing, 1920 April 12; Ruggles to Fulton, 1958 September 20; and Fulton to Ruggles, 1958 September 23. A letter from George Blumer to George Alder Blumer concerning Osler was moved to a folder under George Blumer. George Alder Blumer annotated the context of several of the Osler letters.
- Parant, Victor, Toulouse, 3 letters to George Alder Blumer, 1890 January 28 - 1896 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Tuke, Daniel Hack, Hanwell [England], 2 letters to George Alder Blumer, 1891 February 28 - 1891 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Urquhart, A. R., James Murray's Royal Asylum, Perth, to George Alder Blumer, 1891 March 9 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Welch, William Henry, Baltimore, to George Alder Blumer, 1891 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Yellowlees, David, Royal Asylum, Glasgow, to George Alder Blumer, 1891 February 21 (Box 1, Folder 16)